<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ResearchProject.xsl"?>
<!-- Edited with XML Spy v4.2 -->
<researchproject>

<title>Out-of-core Interactive Display of Large Meshes Using an Oriented Bounding Box-based Hardware Depth Query</title>
<authors>Haeyoung Ha, Benjamin F. Gregorski, Kenneth I. Joy</authors>

<teaser>
<figure>
<image><file width="319" height="210" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/lucyclose_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="319" height="210" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/lucyclose_lit_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="319" height="210" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/lucyclose_back3_cropped.png</file></image>
<caption>
From left to right: Closeup view of the Stanford lucy model showing the front-to-back (light to dark) ordering of the subdivision tree,
lit and shaded image, and side view showing occluded portions of the model.
</caption>
</figure>
</teaser>

<abstract>
In this project we have developed an occlusion culling method that uses hardware-based depth queries on oriented bounding 
boxes to cull unseen geometric primitives efficiently.   
Our methods uses an out-of-core design approach to interactively display models that are too large to fit into main memory.  
There are two main steps to the method:  1) a preprocessing phase and 2) a runtime phase.  
During the preprocessing phase, a spatial subdivision of a given data set is constructed where, 
for each node, an oriented bounding box containing mesh primitives is computed using principal component analysis (PCA).  
At runtime, the subdivision tree is traversed in front-to-back order, 
and only nodes that are determined to be visible---based on the hardware depth query---are rendered.
</abstract>

<section title="Preprocessing">
<text>
The preprocessing phase begins by computing a spatial subdivision 
(Octree or BSP Tree in our implementation) of the mesh to be visualized.  
The mesh consists of vertices and triangles defining the connectivity of the vertices.  
However, this method could easily be extended to handle other types of meshes (or volumes) 
for different types of visualization, such as ray tracing and volume rendering.  
The mesh is recursively partitioned into smaller volumes and an oriented bounding box 
that closely fits the geometry contained within each volume is computed using PCA.  
The subdivision tree and the geometry contained inside each node are stored for use during runtime.  

</text>
</section>

<section title="Runtime">
<text>
At runtime the subdivision tree is traversed in front-to-back order based upon the current view point.
If the node is not visible, traversal is terminated and none of the leaf nodes are rendered, thus saving the time required to render these elements.  
Beginning at the root node, it is determined in which octant (or half-space) the view point lies.  
The dot product between the half-space plane normal and the vector from the viewpoint to the split point of the box 
is used to determine the side of a plane the view point lies.  
For a BSP tree, the plane used is the split plane and front-to-back traversal is simply a variant of an in-order binary tree traversal.  
The child representing the side (front or back) of the split plane that contains the view point is visited first.   
For an octree, three planes are tested to determine the traversal order of the children. 
The local frame for the oriented bounding box implies the three planes that are used.  
A recursive algorithm using bit-toggling (assuming a specific order of children) is used to specify the traversal sequence.
</text>
</section>

<section title="Hardware Depth Queries">
<text>
The hardware occlusion query scan converts a set of graphics primitives (but does not render them to the screen) 
and determines whether or not any pixels in the frame buffer would be affected if the primitives were actually rendered to the screen. 
Our algorithm uses NVIDIA's occlusion query extension and renders the oriented bounding box of a tree node
to determine if the node is visible.
The occlusion query process has three steps:
</text>
<enumerate>
<item>Disable updates to color and depth buffers</item>
<item> Specify the query geometry</item>
<item> Obtain and process query results</item>
</enumerate>
<text>
The result of an occlusion query is not available until the query geometry has finished rasterization, 
which creates a potential for pipeline stalls.  
Keeping the pipeline as full as possible by submitting multiple queries at a time helps alleviate stalls.  
It should be noted that it is possible to lose some amount of culling by submitting multiple queries at once 
if some of the queries are dependent on each other.  
Submitting queries for geometry that overlaps other geometry within a set of queries can potentially lead to 
a false invisibility test.  
(False invisibility tests can cause more than the necessary number of triangles to be rendered, 
but this does not generate cracks or holes in the rendered image.)  
</text>
</section>

<section title="Results">
<figure>
<image><file width="262" height="209" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/dragon_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="262" height="209" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/dragon_lit_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="262" height="209" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/dragon_back_cropped.png</file></image>
<caption>
From left to right: 
Stanford dragon model showing the front-to-back (light to dark) ordering of the subdivision tree,
lit and shaded image, and a top view showing occluded portions of the model.
</caption>
</figure>

<figure>
<image><file width="144" height="325" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/buddha_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="144" height="325" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/buddha_lit_cropped.png</file></image>
<image><file width="144" height="325" >OrientedOcclusionTrees/Pictures/buddha_back_cropped.png</file></image>
<caption>
From left to right: 
Stanford buddha model showing the front-to-back (light to dark) ordering of the subdivision tree,
lit and shaded image, and side view showing occluded portions of the model.
</caption>
</figure>

<text>
Performance results for the occlusion culling, fast rendering from AGP memory,
and a comparison of Octree and <em>Binary Space Partition</em> (BSP) Trees can be found in the paper.
</text>
</section>

<paper file="OrientedOcclusionTrees/OrientedOcclusionTrees.pdf"/>

</researchproject>
