<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ResearchProject.xsl"?>

<researchproject>
<title>Reconstruction of Surfaces from Scattered Data</title>
<authors>
Benjamin F. Gregorski, Bernd Hamann and Kenneth I. Joy
</authors>

<teaser>
<figure>
<image><file width="253" height="200">ScatteredDataReconstruction/StripTreeBoxes.gif</file></image>
<image><file width="253" height="200">ScatteredDataReconstruction/InitialSurfaces.gif</file></image>
<image><file width="253" height="200">ScatteredDataReconstruction/ShadedSurfaces.gif</file></image>
<caption>
<bf>Reconstruction of the skidoo scattered dataset.
Left: Original point set and strip tree nodes; Middle: Fitted surfaces before blending;
Right: Final shaded B-spline surfaces.
</bf>
</caption>
</figure>
</teaser>

<abstract>
In this project we developed a method that constructs a set of B-spline surfaces from 
scattered data points that is usable for further processing in a CAD system. 
There has been a lot of work on reconstructing polygon meshes and other types of 
surfaces from scattered points.
This project focused on solving a subset of the general problem where the desired 
output was topologically equivalent to a single b-spline patch. 
This subset of problems occurs in the design of things like cars, trucks and airplanes and 
so we focused on solving the problem well in this context. 
Our algorithm is in the class of more general clustering methods
that have been used for many applications such as surface simplification, 
surface reconstruction, and collision detection.
</abstract>

<section title="Strip Tree Data Structure">
The basis for our reconstruction is the decomposition of a scattered 
point set into a 3D strip tree. 
Our structure is similar to a quadtree, except that each node in our tree represents a bounding
box whose orientation is defined by the best-fit plane approximating the data points inside a bounding box. 
After each decomposition step, the new tree structure defines a better
appoximation to the underlying data points. 
<p/>
A bounding box for all given data points is computed. 
(The three box axes are parallel to the global coordinate system axes). 
This bounding box is re-oriented so that its three axes are parallel to the three axes 
defined by the principal directions of the underlying point set, obtained by principal
component analysis (PCA). 
This step defines the best-fit (least-squares) plane approximating the data points. 
The figure below shows the root bounding box and the local coordinates frame for the skidoo model obtained
from Hoppe's website at Microsoft.
<figure>
<image><file width="252" height="200">ScatteredDataReconstruction/RootBox.gif</file></image>  
<image><file width="243" height="200">ScatteredDataReconstruction/BoxPoints.gif</file></image>  
<caption>
Left: Root bounding box and local coordinate frame for skidoo model.<br/>
Right: The 16 box points for a 2x2 group of nodes. 
</caption>
</figure>

<p/>
The root bounding box is recursively subdivided until the resulting set of bounding boxes, 
all re-oriented according to their principal directions, approximates the data
points by least squares planes, within a user-defined error tolerance. 
In some cases with sparse data, the subdivision must stop when there are not enough points
to determine a coordinate frame.
The resulting tree of bounding boxes, the strip tree, is used to fit a set of surfaces 
approximating the data points inside each box. 
Once the strip tree is decomposed so that the leaf nodes of the tree all have an error 
below a prespecified error threshold, the strip tree approximation is used to
construct surfaces that approximate the data points in each box. 

</section>

<section title="Surface Fitting">
To construct a least-squares B-spline surface to the points associated with a node, 
the node must first be subdivided. 
The approximation process for a node in the next-to-last level begins with a 
single bi-quadratic B-spline patch fitted to the box points of the node's children. 
The 16 box points for a set of four nodes are shown on the right in the figure above.
The 3x3 control points required for a bi-quadratic B-spline patch are obtained from 
the four corner box points and averages of interior points. 
This set of 4x4 points is reduced to a set of 3x3 points by keeping the four corner points, 
averaging pairs of control points in the middle of the
outside edges, and averaging the four control points in the interior. 
A least-squares bi-quadratic B-spline patch is fitted through the set of 3x3 control points. 
This surface is then degree-elevated to a bi-cubic B-spline patch. 
</section>


<section title="Results">
<figure>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterStripTree.png</file></image>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterShaded.png</file></image>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterWire.png</file></image>
<caption>
Approximation of the Crater Lake dataset using a 32x32 strip tree.
From left to right: The strip tree, shaded surfaces, and wire frame surfaces.
</caption>
</figure>

<figure>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterStripTree64.png</file></image>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterShaded64.png</file></image>
<image><file width="230" height="156">ScatteredDataReconstruction/CraterWire64.png</file></image>
<caption>
Approximation of the Crater Lake dataset using a 64x64 strip tree.
From left to right: The strip tree, shaded surfaces, and wire frame surfaces.
</caption>
</figure>


</section>

PDF versions of the Powerpoint
<link target="ScatteredDataReconstruction/presentation.pdf" text="slides"/> and
<link target="ScatteredDataReconstruction/ScatteredDataReconstruction.pdf" text="paper"/>.

</researchproject>

